# SATHAPPAN MUTHIAH

4607, Wilson Blvd E-mail:sathap1@vt.edu Arlington, VA-22203 Work Permit: F1 until 2019 Phone:801-201-0619

#### SUMMARY

Phd student working in spatio-temporal event forecasting using open-source indicators (OSI) with specific focus on making predictions with reasoning. Experienced with working on big data, text and time series mining. Broadly interested in maching learning, temporal mining and data science.

# **EDUCATION**

• PhD in Computer Science

June 2014 — present Arlington, VA

Virginia Tech *GPA*: 3.80

Advisor: Dr. Naren Ramakrishnan

• MS. in Computer Science

Jan 2012 — June 2014 Arlington, VA

Virginia Tech GPA: 3.82

Advisor: Dr. Naren Ramakrishnan

• B.Tech. in Information Tech.

2007 — 2011 Bhopal, India

GPA: 8.65

National Institute of Tech.

## Professional Experience

• Virginia Tech

GRA, Discovery Analytics Center

Spring 2012 — Present Arlington, VA

- IARPA FUNGCAT: Design and Development of deep Learning models capable of predicting the protein function of a given gene sequence.
- IARPA MERCURY: Establishing techniques for fusing alerts from multiple streams (or models).
- IARPA OSI: Worked on real-time forecasting of spatio-temporal events like Civil Unrest
- Handled streaming, ingestion (Web Scraping or via API) and enrichment of several publicly available data sources like News, Blogs, Facebook events, Twitter
- Implemented big data unrest forecasting pipeline in python over AWS cluster framework
- Collaborated with several institutes such as NDSSL (at VT), University of Maryland, CACI, Basis Tech.,
  University of California-San Diego and San Diego State University, USC Information Sciences Institute
- Press coverage: http://www.cccblog.org/2012/09/22/building-a-data-eye-in-the-sky/

# • Indian Institute of Scientific Education and Research

Nov2008 — Jan 2009

Intern, advised by Dr. Prashanta Panigrahi

Kolkata, India

- Studied the feasibility of a quantum computing system using common and attainable finite dimensional multipartite quantum states.

### • National Institute of Oceanography

Intern, mentored by Dr. Biswajit Chakraborty

May-June 2010 Goa, India

 Estimated geophysical parameters using SONAR Backscatter data obtained off an experiment on the Western Continental shelf of India. Developed processing and cleansing techniques to process backscatter data and used simplex method for estimation.

# PUBLICATIONS

- D. K. Gupta, S. Muthiah, D. Mares, and N. Ramakrishnan. Forecasting Civil Strife: An Emerging Methodology. In *HUSO The Third International Conference on Human and Social Analytics*, 2017
- P. Chakraborty, S. Muthiah, R. Tandon, and N. Ramakrishnan. Hierarchical Quickest Change Detection via Surrogates. arXiv preprint arXiv:1603.09739, 2016

- S. Muthiah, B. Huang, J. Arredondo, D. Mares, L. Getoor, G. Katz, and N. Ramakrishnan. Capturing planned protests from open source indicators. *AI Magazine*, 37(2), 2016
- S. Muthiah, P. Butler, R. P. Khandpur, P. Saraf, N. Self, A. Rozovskaya, L. Zhao, J. Cadena, C.-T. Lu, A. Vullikanti, A. Marathe, K. Summers, G. Katz, A. Doyle, J. Arredondo, D. K. Gupta, D. Mares, and N. Ramakrishnan. Embers at 4 years: Experiences operating an open source indicators forecasting system. In *Proceedings of the 22Nd ACM SIGKDD International Conference on Knowledge Discovery and Data Mining*, KDD '16, pages 205–214, New York, NY, USA, 2016. ACM
- Y. Ning, S. Muthiah, H. Rangwala, and N. Ramakrishnan. Modeling precursors for event forecasting via nested multi-instance learning. In *Proceedings of the 22Nd ACM SIGKDD International Conference on Knowledge Discovery and Data Mining*, KDD '16, pages 1095–1104, New York, NY, USA, 2016. ACM
- S. Muthiah, B. Huang, J. Arredondo, et al. Planned Protest Modeling in News and Social Media. In AAAI Conference on Artificial Intelligence, January 25-30, 2015, pages 3920–3927, 2015
- J. Schlachter, A. Ruvinsky, L. A. Reynoso, S. Muthiah, and N. Ramakrishnan. Leveraging topic models to develop metrics for evaluating the quality of narrative threads extracted from news stories. *Procedia Manufacturing*, 3:4028–4035, 2015
- Y. Ning, S. Muthiah, R. Tandon, and N. Ramakrishnan. Uncovering news-twitter reciprocity via interaction patterns. In Advances in Social Networks Analysis and Mining (ASONAM), 2015 IEEE/ACM International Conference on, pages 1–8. IEEE, 2015
- N. Ramakrishnan, P. Butler, S. Muthiah, N. Self, et al. 'Beating the news' with EMBERS: Forecasting Civil Unrest using Open Source Indicators. In *International Conference on Knowledge Discovery and Data Mining, KDD, August 24 27, 2014*, pages 1799–1808, 2014
- A. Doyle, G. Katz, K. Summers, C. Ackermann, I. Zavorin, Z. Lim, S. Muthiah, P. Butler, N. Self, L. Zhao, et al. Forecasting significant societal events using the embers streaming predictive analytics system. *Big Data*, 2(4):185–195, 2014

### ACTIVITIES

- Intellectual Property: P. Butler, S. Muthiah, and N. Ramakrishnan. Alert Generation from Multiple Streams, 2016. VTIP 17-047
- Program Committee: ACM SIGKDD 2018, ASONAM 2018

### AWARDS AND HONORS

Student Travel Award
 KDD
 Pratt Fellowship
 Virginia Tech
 Deployed Application Paper Award
 IAAI

### TECHNICAL SKILLS

- Programming: Python, C/C++, R, Java, Matlab, HTML, PHP
- Frameworks: NOSQL: MongoDB, ElasticSearch, Tensorflow, MapReduce

### Participation in Conferences

- KDD 2016, 22nd ACM SIGKDD International Conference on Knowledge Discovery and Data Mining, San Francisco, USA, August 2016.
- KDD 2015, 21st ACM SIGKDD International Conference on Knowledge Discovery and Data Mining, Sydney, Australia, August 2015.
- IAAI 2014, 27th Conference on Innovative Applications of Artificial Intelligence, Austin, USA, Jan 2014.